so ajan I find myself full of energy
when engaging in things that aren't
beneficial for me but surprisingly lazy
when it comes to activities that are
generally advantageous
it's not a lack of energy rather I seem
to misdirect it
why is this the case why can't I Channel
this energy towards achieving nibana
which is the ultimate source of true
benefit because that energy is based on
because that energy is based on
sensuality
same I mean why is it easier to not keep
the precepts and go out and party and
not work hard and not save money but
spend everything and
because it's less resistance
means it's easier to have energy and
inspiration to do it
so it's going to hurt initially say try
try installing any discipline in your
life from a non-disciplined behavior point of
from a non-disciplined behavior point of
view you're going to suffer initially
what that person seems to be asking is
how can I having not been disciplined
become disciplined and have the same
type of non-discipline inspiration for
developing on my discipline
and that's just contradiction in terms
first you're going to suffer on account
of giving up your undisciplined ways and
intoxications gonna have some withdrawal symptoms yeah
gonna have some withdrawal symptoms yeah
then if you would have established
yourself in that then discipline and
Paths of
more resistance that require more effort
but it could have a greater reward they
will become easier you will be actually
inspired to do it
that's why even the Buddha in the suit
that says that he experienced tireless
energy only after he is completely surmounted
only after he is completely surmounted
unholesome thoughts
when he stopped giving in to unwholesome
actions by Body speech and then mentally
when he only thought
good thoughts that he only allowed
thoughts they were rooted in in
wholesome intentions then he had a
tireless energy and inspiration
when he completely withdrawn himself
from an awesome States
and when you think about it that is the
true type of effortlessness
when you established yourself in that
balanced state of withdrawal from
unwholesome because even sensuality
requires effort
it's just that charity on top of the
cake masks the fact that you are still
working hard and sweating and enduring
on account of it you don't see that
because you all you see is the carrot in
front of you
you don't see the whip the bird and you
have to carry the implications only
later when when you have eaten the
carrot so the point is you recognize that even
so the point is you recognize that even
that is not effortless it's actually
although you might be inspired and full
of energy it's quite a quite a kind of
hardest task to do it
the only true effortlessness is when you
are withdrawn from unwholesome there is
no more burden pressuring you
uh then that's just completely
unobstructed energy left
because there's nothing pressuring it
from left to right
and there's a
this kind of
it's a quote I found regarding those
questions says the benefits that come from
says the benefits that come from
renunciation of sensuality far surpassed
the difficulties one Encounters in doing
so hmm yeah exactly
conversely pursuing sensuality for the
fleeting Pleasures it offers pales in
comparison to the immense hardships it
brings upon oneself yeah yeah if you
think about it like entire people's
lives
you know for decades are the result of
their Central cravings
of of the immediate nature oh I want
this or that and they end up enduring an
account of it for years or endlessly
till the end of their life if they have
accumulated too much that they can't
just shake off now that burden
everything from like family children
Duty tasks work pressure stress
all of that is the result of you wanting
to have access to as much sincerity as
possible which do you ever have which
was never enough obviously but again you
you fall you fall prey of your own kind
of lack of reasoning really and
discipline like you can reason all you
want but unless you start applying this
it's not gonna it's not gonna work but
that's the point even even people that
have recognized if they give up the
immediate seeking of the immediate
gratification careless gratification
what used to be uninspiring hard thing
to do they'll start to enjoy
this they'll enjoy doing crafts or
manual labor and so on but they're
giving up because the mind has has sort
of dried up from that expectation of
immediate reward and gratification that
comes on a kind of quick sense sent
engagement pleasure sensing agent
pleasure but if you keep going that way
that expectation builds up and then even
the most mundane thing such as sitting
doing nothing and breeding will become
intolerable difficult time it will be border he's
difficult time it will be border he's
like depression he will not be able to
Bear it unless it's that level of
immediate gratifying but if you start
withdrawing from it you know stuff that
was kind of unimaginable to do like well
I could never sit and learn how to do
this and be so patient or or deal with
the boredom or just as I said mundanely
learn how to do a craft that takes years
to develop that will become pure
pleasure to do if you're withdrawn from
that immediate or from that expectations
for immediate gratification and
immediate pleasure
so it's like again untrained untrained
animal if you let let it run loose and
wild it will only get wild there
if you start containing it restraining
it directing it rightly it will came
down which means the wild ways would now
be harder to do
so initially that
pronunciation is
seemingly very difficult exactly a major
hardship very quickly
you get the pleasure from it which is
fast which fast passes that you know
that makes that hardship seem and
surpasses it because like it because it
offers you what you always fundamentally
seek which is peace
which is equilibrium which is
importability that's what people chase
the essential desires
because that is the the implication
there is that once you get what you want
you will be satisfied I.E peaceful you
will be evened out and at ease
but if you try to get the peace through
the desires
it's not only very fleeting it's not
even peace to be to begin with
it's really more like just fatigue as a
result of of pursuit of their desire
that's now been sort of annulled quickly
and you are left with that same kind of
uh
so for now I'm peaceful relatively
because I can't be bothered because I'm
too tired basically
but then when the itch appears again
when the pressure comes again you have
no other recoils than to give into it
and try to find ways of scratching it
and appeasing it which means you're
constantly yoked and pulled and and and
and pressured
so you read the true peace then is to
not be pressured by that desire to begin
with and again we're speaking colloquially
and again we're speaking colloquially
not even from the point of view of you
know serious commitment to the Dharma
practice and so on even if you're not
interested in pursuing the the teaching
of the Buddha and so on if you're
actually invest effort in taming your
desires and gaining some self-control
when it comes to it you're gonna have a
more peaceful mind actually
you're going to have a less rebellious
mind less irrational mind
less anxious mind
and then tasks
duties things that life kind of causes
that you have to deal with
will not be as overwhelming
because you will not shy away from Duty
or as I said uh difficult things that
take time to perform and patience to get
results and so on because you're already
peaceful because you're already exactly
you're already have seized to value that
instant gratification so if there is no
immediate reward I can't do this
that expectation has been built up
through your carelessness in in same way
that expectation can be undone through
your carefully attending and investing
effort and discipline